Kamal Ziaul Islam

LinkedIn | GitHub | Google Citation

Location: 20 University Dr, Corner Brook, NL Email: kzislam@grenfell.mun.ca | Mobile: 709 639 2607

CLIMATE CHANGE RESEARCHER

I am a highly skilled hydrological modeler with over **2 years of experience** in **Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT) model, Hydrus-1D, CropWat model**. I have knowledge of popular programming such as **Python, and R** and experience with the Statistical package **Minitab** and also developed data analysis and scientific report writing skills.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Hydrological model : SWAT, Hydrus-1D, SPAW (Soil Plant Air Water), CropWat

Climate model : Statistical Downscaling (SDSM)

Computer programing : R, Python, C++, **Statistical Package** : Minitab, XLstat

GIS and Remote Sensing: ArcGIS, QGIS, Google Earth Engine

Document Preparation: LaTeX, Overleaf

EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant

May 2022 - Present

Corner Brook, NL

Grenfell Campus, Memorial University

- Field scale hydrological modeling using **Hydrus-1D**. Conducted fieldwork to collect data on soil properties, vegetation cover, topography, and climate.
- Contributed to a greater understanding of the complex interactions between soil, water, and vegetation.

Engineer in Training

May 2022 - Dec 2022

Grenfell Campus, Memorial University

Corner Brook, NL

- Assist Facilities Management and maintenance staff with project management work and documentation and progress reporting of various on-site construction projects and upcoming works.
- Site assessments and tracking of work against proposed scheduling, and other associated duties.

Teaching Assistant

May 2021 – April 2022

Grenfell Campus, Memorial University

Corner Brook, NL

• Assist the course instructor with daily duties including grading assignments and offering additional support to students for using **Minitab**.

Deputy General Manager

2016 - 2021

Jessore PBS, BREB

Jessore, Bangladesh

- Developed policies, procedures, guidelines, and priorities to achieve established goals.
- Managed projects and programs with engineers, planning, scheduling, and coordinating activities.
- Lead regional water resource initiatives focused on sustainable and efficient water; irrigation, drainage, flood protection, water supply, and natural system needs.
- Integrated climate science and climate change considerations across all aspects of program activities, giving emphasis on addressing impacts of sea-level rise and precipitation changes.
- Supported the Zonal's resilience initiative and efforts as a partner in the Southwest Regional Climate Change impact.
- Prepared and managed operational and capital budgets, pursuing funding opportunities and partnerships.
- Managed the execution of program reports and tracked performance, producing agency correspondence, briefing documents, and presentations.

Assistant General Manager

2007 - 2021

Kushtia PBS, BREB

Kushtia, Bangladesh

• Developed solutions to agricultural problems concerned with power and machinery, electrification, structures, soil, and water conservation, improving the process of agricultural products, and applying agricultural engineering technology.

- Plan, design, and construct Irrigation and Drainage facilities and rural electrification.
- Lead project management and contract administration of District Irrigation and Drainage facilities including the construction system, distribution system, and related facilities.
- Managed and supervised the activities of staff; planned section work programs and managed project goals, assigned tasks, and oversees work efforts, provided supervision.

EDUCATION

PhD candidate, Transdisciplinary Sustainability doctoral program

Grenfell Campus, Memorial University

Corner Brook,NL, Canada *May 2022*

Master of Science in Sustainable Water Management

Kristianstad University

Kristianstad, Sweden Sept 2010 – Jun 2012

Master of Science in Farm Structure

Mymensingh, Bangladesh Jul 2005 – Jun 2007

Bangladesh Agricultural University

Jul 2005 – Juli 2007

Bachelor of Science in Agricultural Engineering

Bangladesh Agricultural University

Mymensingh, Bangladesh Jul 1997 – Jun 2002

SHORT COURSES

Fundamental of GIS

Davis, California, USA

2018

University of California (Davis)

Introduction to GIS Mapping

University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada 2023

RESEARCH PROJECTS

Climate Change Research

Upper Humber River Watershed Model

SWAT Model

- To quantify the impacts of climate change on the spatial and temporal availability of water resources at the upper Humber River watershed.
- To investigate the Climate Change Impact on the Crop Water Requirement of cereal crops and root vegetables.
- To assess the impact of climate change on agricultural sustainability in Western NL.

Hydrological Modeling

Agricultural field scale

Hydrus-1D

- Measuring the Impact of Crop Rotation on Agricultural in Western Newfoundland
- Estimate the water budget components of a corn field and assess the temporal variability of water content in shallow soil profiles.

PUBLICATION

- Faruque, M. J., Vekerdy, Z., Hasan, M. Y., **Islam, K. Z.**, Young, B., Ahmed, M. T., ... Kundu, P. (2022). Monitoring of land use and land cover changes by using remote sensing and GIS techniques at human-induced mangrove forests areas in Bangladesh. Remote Sensing Applications: Society and Environment, 25, 100699. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rsase.2022.100699
- Islam, K. Z., Islam, M. S., Lacoursière, J. O., Dessborn, L. (2014). Low-Cost Rainwater Harvesting: An Alternate Solution to Salinity Affected Coastal Region of Bangladesh. American Journal of Water Resources, 2(6), 141-148. https://doi.org/10.12691/ajwr-2-6-2

VOLUNTEERING

Member VP In Person Member Academic Council, Graduate Student Rep. Grenfell Graduate Student Society Bangladesh Red Crescent Society Grenfell Campus, MUN Grenfell Campus, MUN Satkhira, Bangladesh

REFERENCES

References are provided upon request.